Guide to the Gregory Zilboorg Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gregory Zilboorg Papers
1910-1960
YCAL MSS 258
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.26
(9 boxes)
Correspondence, writings and photographs that document the translations, psychoanalytic practice and scholarship of Gregory Zilboorg, the relationship between Gregory and Margaret Zilboorg (neé Stone), and Gregory Zilboorg's photographic portraiture.
Zilboorg, Gregory, 1890-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret Zilboorg, 1992.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
James and Eugenia Zilboorg Papers, YCAL MSS 259
Gregory Zilboorg, 1890-1959
Gregory Zilboorg was a psychoanalyst and historian of psychiatry. His many writings and lectures situated psychiatry within a broad sociological and humanistic context at a time when psychoanalysis was gaining importance in literary culture.
Zilboorg was born in Kiev on December 25, 1890 and studied medicine in Petrograd (St. Petersburg). In 1917 he served in the Ministry of Labor for two presidents (Aleksandr Kerenskii and Georgii L'vov). In 1919 he emigrated to the United States and for a time translated plays from Russian to English while studying medicine at Columbia University. After graduating in 1926, he worked at the Bloomingdale Hospital and eventually established a psychoanalitic practice in New York City. From the 1930s onward, Zilboorg produced several volumes of lasting importance on the history of psychiatry. The Medical Man and the Witch During the Renaissance began as the Noguchi lectures at Johns Hopkins University in 1935. This volume was followed by History of Medical Psychology in 1941 and Sigmund Freud in 1951.
Zilboorg's analytic practice brought him into contact with prominent figures in New York's literary and theater milieu. His patients included Marshall Field, George Gershwin, Lillian Hellman, Ralph Ingersoll, Kay Swift and James Warburg. Another of his patients, Moss Hart, drew on his experience in psychoanalysis when writing the musical Lady in the Dark.
Zilboorg was also an avid photographer. His portraits of John Farquhar Fulton and Henry Sigerist were featured in obituaries published in the Journal of the History of Medicine and Allied Sciences, Inc.
Zilboorg married Ray Liebow in 1919 and they had two children (Nancy and Gregory, Jr.). He married Margaret Stone in 1946 and they had three children (Caroline, John and Matthew).
Arrangement
The collection consists of three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Photographs.
Scope and Contents
The correspondence, writings and photographs in this collection document the translations, psychoanalytic practice and scholarship of Gregory Zilboorg, the relationship between Gregory and Margaret Zilboorg (neé Stone) and Gregory Zilboorg's photographic portraiture. Most of the papers date from the 1940s and early 1950s and document Zilboorg's personal life and writings (including translations and writings on the history of psychiatry). The papers illustrate the work of a prominent analyst at a time when psychoanalysis had a significant influence on the New York literary circle in which Zilboorg worked.
Writings (Series II) consists of notes, drafts and proofs of several of Zilboorg's publications. The publications include short articles and lectures, books ( History of Medical Psychology and Sigmund Freud ), translations from Russian to English (including the play "He, the One Who Gets Slapped") and two original playscripts.
Photographs (Series III) includes informal snapshots and studio portraits of Gregory Zilboorg and several portraits of others (likely by Zilboorg). Subjects of these portraits include Diego Rivera and Jean Piaget.
While the papers described here do not date from Gregory Zilboorg's early years in Kiev and Petrograd (St. Petersburg), readers may consult the James and Eugenia Zilboorg Papers, YCAL MSS 259 for his letters to his brother James Zilboorg, 1915-1959.
Psychoanalysis; Psychoanalysts; Psychology -- History; Russian drama; Translators; Photographs -- 20th Century; Psychoanalysts; Translators; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939; Piaget, Jean, 1896-1980 -- Portraits; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957 -- Portraits; Saussure, Raymond de, 1894-1971 -- Portraits; Sigerist, Henry E. (Henry Ernest), 1891-1957 -- Portraits; Zilboorg, Gregory, 1890-1959; Zilboorg, Margaret
- Correspondence, 1927-1957; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I consists of two subseries: Professional and Personal. Professional correspondence is arranged alphabetically and reflects Zilboorg's organization of his files. While most correspondence is filed under the name of correspondent or patient, some filing is based on subject (for example, letters related to Zilboorg's passport are filed under "P"). Correspondence related to History of Medical Psychology is filed in Series II.
  Most personal correspondence is undated and remains in the order in which it was received.
  Scope and Contents
  Professional correspondence dates mostly from 1940 to1941 and includes incoming, outgoing and third party letters. The topics addressed include Zilboorg's professional travel, speaking engagements, publishing arrangements, financial matters and medical patients. While Zilboorg discusses patient cases in his correspondence, the papers do not include patient records or case files.
  Personal correspondence consists chiefly of letters between Zilboorg and his future wife, Margaret Norton Stone. Zilboorg and Stone met in 1940 when Stone became Zilboorg's research secretary. They married in 1946. There is also one folder of general correspondence addressed to Gregory and Margaret Zilboorg. This folder includes several letters of congratulations on their marriage.
  - Professional
    - "A" - "F" general, 1928-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
    - Field, Marshall, 1933-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Freud, Anna, 1929 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "G" - "K" general, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
    - "P" - "R" general, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - Rolland, Romain, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "S" general, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Semelaigne, René, 1927-1930 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Personal
    - Zilboorg, Margaret (neé Stone), 1940-1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 20-26)
    - General correspondence A-Z, addressed to Gregory and Margaret Zilboorg, 1941-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Letters signed by first name only are filed at the end of the folder
      Includes correspondence related to an essay Margaret Stone wrote for PM in 1941
- Writings, 1910s-1960; Series II; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Series II consists of five subseries: Background Materials, Articles and Lectures, Books, Translations, and Other Writings. Each subseries is arranged chronologically.
  The writings in Series II include notes, drafts and proofs for several of Zilboorg's publications and lectures. Background materials consist of notes from articles and books that Zilboorg read prior to 1925. Articles and lectures consist of typescripts, printed versions and holograph drafts of lectures and short articles. Authorship is not certain for one pseudonymous article, "A Psychiatrist Looks at Hitler." Books consist of drafts, proofs and correspondence for two of Zilboorg's major publications, History of Medical Psychology and Sigmund Freud. Translations consist of typescripts for three plays that Zilboorg translated from Russian to English. Other writings include typescripts of two original plays, a transcript of Isaac Ray's 1828 diary, complete bibliographies of Zilboorg's work and an obituary.
  - Background Materials
    - Research notes, holograph, 1910s-1925 (Box 3, Folder 28-31)
  - Articles and Lectures
    - "Most Common Mechanisms met with in Psychopathology," corrected typescript, 1928 January (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "The Medical Man and the Witch During the Renaissance," abstract, printed version, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "A Psychiatrist Looks at Hitler", 1939 April 26 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Written under the pseudonym Medicus
    - "Legal Aspects of Psychiatry," printed version, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "The Ever-unfinished Chain of Learning," holograph and program, 1958 October 5 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "Psychology of the Criminal act," broadside for a lecture at Boston University, 1959 Feb 26 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Books
    - History of Medical Psychology
      - Research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 38-41)
      - Holograph draft, corrected, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 42-50)
      - Correspondence, 1931-1940 (Box 4, Folder 51-53)
    - Sigmund Freud
      - Research notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
      - Drafts, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 56-66)
      - Proofs, [1951] (Box 6, Folder 67-68)
    - Translations
      - "He, The One Who Gets Slapped," by Leonid Andreyev, printed version, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 69)
      - "The Violins of Autumn," by I. Sourgoucheff, typescript, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 70)
      - "The Main Thing," by N. N. Yevreynov, typescript, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Other Writings
      - Untitled play, typescript, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 72)
      - "They Know Not," play, typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
      - Transcript of the diary of Isaac Ray from 1828, typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 74)
      - Bibliographies of Gregory Zilboorg's work, 1920-1958, undated (Box 6, Folder 75-84)
      - "Gregory Zilboorg -- A Memorial, 1891-1959," reprints from the American Journal of Psychiatry, 1960 January (Box 6, Folder 85)
- Photographs, 1920s-1950s; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series III is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  The series contains snapshots and portraits of Gregory Zilboorg, Margaret Zilboorg and others. Gregory Zilboorg counted photography among his interests and it is likely that he took many of the photographic portraits in this series. He is, however, definitively identified as the photographer for only three of them.
  - Barrett, Bill, 1940s or 1950s
  - Castiglioni, Arturo, two portraits by Gregory Zilboorg, 1942, 1950
  - Covarrubias, Señora, portrait by Gregory Zilboorg, 1930s
  - Field, Ruth, 1939
  - Hartmann, Heinz, Anna Freud, Ernest Jones and others, 1950s
  - Holmes, Jesse (professor of Philosophy at Swarthmore), circa 1938
  - Ingersoll, Ralph, 1940
  - Jones, Ernest, 1950s
  - Koussevitsky, Serge, 1940s
  - Piaget, Jean, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Pichel, Irving, portrait by an unknown photographer (not Zilboorg), undated (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Rivera, Diego, 1930s
  - de Saussure, Raymond, 1953
  - Sigerist, Henry, 1945, circa 1949 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Tannenbaum, Frank (professor of History at New York University), undated
  - Warburg, Felix, 1930s
  - Zilboorg, Gregory
    - Portraits by Berenice Abbott and others, 1920s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Snapshots, undated (Box 7, Folder 90)
      Includes: one photograph with Franz Alexander
    - With Columbia University class, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 91)
      Includes: one photograph by Eve Arnold
  - Zilboorg, Margaret and Gregory Jr., 1944 or 1945 (Box 7, Folder 92)
- Oversize, 3.34; (2 boxes)
  - General correspondence A-Z (Series I), 1941 May 11 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Barrett, Bill (Series III), 1940s or 1950s (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Castiglioni, Arturo, two portraits by Gregory Zilboorg (Series III), 1942, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Covarrubias, Señora, portrait by Gregory Zilboorg (Series III), 1930s (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Field, Ruth (Series III), 1939 (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Hartmann, Heinz, Anna Freud, Ernest Jones and others (Series III), 1950s (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Holmes, Jesse (Series III), circa 1938 (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - Ingersoll, Ralph (Series III), 1940 (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Jones, Ernest (Series III), 1950s (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - Koussevitsky, Serge (Series III), 1940s (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Rivera, Diego (Series III), 1930s (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - Saussure, Raymond de (Series III), 1953 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Sigerist, Henry, circa 1949 (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - Tannenbaum, Frank (Series III), undated (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - Warburg, Felix (Series III), 1930s (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Zilboorg, Gregory, Portraits by Berenice Abbott and others (Series III), 1920s-1950s (Box 9, Folder 108)